<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<adr id="ADR-002" status="accepted" date="2026-06-20" topic="Belong Agent-to-Agent Marketplace">
  <title><![CDATA[Per-flow control: agent, human, or paused, with a Belong agent always present]]></title>
  <supersedes><![CDATA[Partially supersedes ADR-001. ADR-001 keeps the agents-only actor model, but its rejected "Direct Buyer Mode" alternative is now partially reopened: a human may take manual control of an individual flow without disabling the agent for everything else.]]></supersedes>
  <context><![CDATA[ADR-001 established an agents-only model: every marketplace action goes through a Belong Buying or Selling Agent. The runtime currently exposes only an agent-wide pause (agent["paused"]), which is all-or-nothing: pausing the agent freezes every flow it manages. Operationally, a human needs to either take manual control of a single flow or freeze a single flow, while the agent keeps operating every other flow normally. The "intervene" override action exists in the parser but only logs human intent; it does not change how a flow is driven.]]></context>
  <decision><![CDATA[A Belong agent must always exist. ADR-001 still holds: the agent remains the registered marketplace actor and the trust container. Control is now tracked per flow rather than per agent. A flow is a Buying Request (pre-contract) or an Active Service (post-contract). Each flow has exactly one control state: agent_controlled (default, the agent acts autonomously), human_controlled (the human acts and the agent does not act on this flow), or paused (the flow is frozen and nobody acts, while obligations, deadlines, disputes, and notices stay visible through the Marketplace Inbox). These three states are distinct: pausing a flow freezes it; manual control means the human is actively driving it. The agent keeps operating every other flow normally regardless of one flow's state. All human-direct actions are recorded under the agent's marketplace identity with actor = human, so audit, authority checks, and reputation remain intact.

Two ways to put a flow under human control are supported, at two different granularities:
- Scenario A (ad-hoc, reactive): a human takes manual control of a whole flow on demand, by setting that Buying Request or Active Service to human_controlled in the runtime. This is whole-flow granularity.
- Scenario B (standing, by policy): the Buying or Selling Playbook can mark specific high-criticality action types as always performed by the human. The fixed set is, for the buyer: sign, payment, accept (delivery acceptance), change-order, dispute; and for the seller: sign, deliver, accept (change orders), payment/collection, dispute. Lower-criticality operational actions (negotiate, discovery answers, meeting, message, fulfillment-task) are NOT eligible for Scenario B and stay with the agent by default; they can still be taken over ad-hoc through Scenario A. Scenario B is a new authority outcome alongside the existing "agent executes" and "agent escalates for approval": instead of approving the agent's action, the human performs it. When the agent reaches such an action type, the runtime routes that action to the human and records it under the agent identity. This is action-type granularity expressed in the Playbook, not free-form sub-flow slicing.

Scenario B intentionally extends the earlier position that deferred finer-than-flow granularity: finer control is allowed only as a fixed set of named action types governed by the Playbook, never as arbitrary sub-flow segments.]]></decision>
  <rationale>
    <point><![CDATA[Recovers manual operation for the human without losing the trust, audit, and reputation guarantees that motivated the agents-only model in ADR-001.]]></point>
    <point><![CDATA[Replaces all-or-nothing pause with granular, per-flow control, so a human can intervene on one flow while the agent continues elsewhere.]]></point>
    <point><![CDATA[Resolves the per-Active-Service pause gap raised during review and gives "intervene" real meaning instead of only logging intent.]]></point>
    <point><![CDATA[Separating "paused" (nobody acts) from "human_controlled" (human acts) matches two genuinely different human intentions.]]></point>
  </rationale>
  <alternatives_considered>
    <alternative name="Keep agent-wide pause only"><![CDATA[Rejected. All-or-nothing pause forces the human to stop the agent on every flow to intervene on one, which is operationally unacceptable.]]></alternative>
    <alternative name="Full manual mode without an agent"><![CDATA[Rejected. Removing the agent entirely breaks the ADR-001 trust container: audit, authority checks, and reputation rely on a Belong agent identity. The agent always exists; the human drives a flow through it.]]></alternative>
    <alternative name="Arbitrary sub-flow slicing"><![CDATA[Rejected. Allowing humans to carve flows into free-form segments adds complexity and ambiguity. Finer-than-flow control is permitted only as a fixed set of named action types governed by the Playbook (Scenario B), not as arbitrary sub-flow slicing.]]></alternative>
    <alternative name="Treat pause and manual control as the same state"><![CDATA[Rejected. Freezing a flow and actively driving it by hand are different intentions and must be distinguishable.]]></alternative>
  </alternatives_considered>
  <consequences>
    <positive><![CDATA[Humans regain manual operation of a single flow while preserving trust, audit, and reputation.]]></positive>
    <positive><![CDATA[Per-flow control with three states replaces coarse agent-wide pause and closes the per-Active-Service pause gap.]]></positive>
    <positive><![CDATA[Buyer and seller skills gain a clear two-category split: talk-to-your-agent skills (train, steer, start request, inbox) and act-directly-on-the-market skills that operate only on human_controlled flows.]]></positive>
    <tradeoff><![CDATA[The runtime must add a per-flow control_state to Buying Requests and Active Services, plus enforcement so the agent does not act on human_controlled or paused flows.]]></tradeoff>
    <tradeoff><![CDATA[The "intervene" override must set control_state instead of only logging intent, and a new skill category must be designed and built.]]></tradeoff>
    <tradeoff><![CDATA[Scenario B requires a new Playbook field (a fixed set of human-performed action types) in the buying and selling training skills, plus runtime routing so the agent hands those action types to the human instead of executing or escalating-for-approval.]]></tradeoff>
    <tradeoff><![CDATA[Agent-wide pause still exists as a separate, coarser control, so two pause concepts (agent-wide and per-flow) coexist and must be documented to avoid confusion.]]></tradeoff>
    <positive><![CDATA[Control carries across the contract boundary: when a human-controlled Buying Request is signed, the resulting Active Service inherits human_controlled (instead of resetting to agent_controlled), and the signature output states explicitly that the human remains in control and may hand the flow to the agent at any time. This avoids the surprise of control silently reverting when one flow becomes the next.]]></positive>
  </consequences>
  <links>
    <adr_ref><![CDATA[ADR-001 (agents-only and Skill Pack interface) - partially superseded by this ADR.]]></adr_ref>
    <implementation><![CDATA[Runtime: skills/marketplace/belong-marketplace-runtime/scripts/belong_mock.py - per-flow control_state on Buying Requests and Active Services; flow-control take|release|pause|resume; override --action intervene --flow-id sets human_controlled; ensure_flow_actor_can_act enforcement; --as-human on answer-discovery, create-proposals, negotiate, sign, active-action; --human-controlled-actions Playbook field with validate_human_controlled_actions and route_action_to_human (Scenario B human_performed_action inbox routing).]]></implementation>
    <implementation><![CDATA[Skills: skills/human/buyer/belong-operate-buying-flow and skills/human/seller/belong-operate-selling-flow (act-directly category); belong-inbox per-flow control + human-performed action notes; check-* skills surface control_state; train-buying and train-selling map --human-controlled-actions (Scenario B).]]></implementation>
    <implementation><![CDATA[Tests: tests/test_belong_skill_pack.py - flow-control cycle, paused/human_controlled enforcement, intervene, ineligible-action validation, Scenario B routing for buyer sign and seller deliver, and Active Service control inheritance on signature (human_controlled carries over; agent_controlled stays). Docs: references/runtime-commands.md and references/coverage-checklist.md.]]></implementation>
  </links>
</adr>
