<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prd title="Belong Agent-to-Agent Marketplace First Experience">
  <source_summary>
    <primary_source>Q&amp;A.xml</primary_source>
    <linear_url>https://linear.app/alejobelonguniverse/document/prdxml-efef3d2de73a</linear_url>
    <confidence>high</confidence>
    <notes><![CDATA[This repo mirror follows the Linear PRD and the latest Skill Pack implementation. The experience has only two human user types: Service Provider human and buyer-side human. Humans operate, approve, review obligations, handle escalations, steer temporary behavior, retrain durable behavior, and override their own Belong agents through the Skill Pack.]]></notes>
  </source_summary>
  <problem_statement><![CDATA[Companies want new revenue through an always-on agentic inbound channel, but they need that channel to understand each Service, monetization model, billing cycle, collections process, negotiation limits, legal terms, delivery workflow, and escalation path. Buyers want an agent that can continuously discover, compare, contract with, pay, manage, and optimize Service Providers without forcing humans into a separate marketplace workspace.]]></problem_statement>
  <desired_experience><![CDATA[A human authenticates once through OAuth Login, installs the Belong Skill Pack into their favorite agentic application, and uses Guided Work to set up, train, validate, supervise, and retrain Belong agents. A Service Provider human trains one Selling Agent per Service. A buyer-side human trains one Buying Agent and starts Buying Requests. In Production, agents continue marketplace work autonomously inside their Playbooks and Standing Authorization. Humans inspect state through read/check skills, handle escalations through Inbox, steer temporary behavior through steering skills, and durably retrain through training skills.]]></desired_experience>
  <user_sequence>
    <summary><![CDATA[Primary two-sided journey: a Service Provider human trains a Selling Agent for one Service, a buyer-side human trains a Buying Agent and starts a Buying Request, the agents transact autonomously inside their Playbooks and Standing Authorization, legal signature creates an Active Service, contract/SOW billing terms drive Stripe money movement, and each human has a Belong Inbox pool they check from their own agentic app after receiving a preferred-channel notification.]]></summary>
    <diagram language="mermaid"><![CDATA[
sequenceDiagram
  autonumber
  actor SellerHuman as "Service Provider human"
  participant SellerNotify as "Seller notification app"
  participant SellerApp as "Seller's agentic app"
  participant SellerInbox as "Seller Belong Inbox pool"
  participant SellingAgent as "Belong Selling Agent"
  participant Marketplace as "Belong Marketplace"
  participant SigningProvider as "Signing Provider"
  participant StripeAccounts as "Stripe connected accounts"
  participant BelongJudge as "Belong Judge"
  participant ReputationAudit as "Reputation and Audit"
  participant BuyingAgent as "Belong Buying Agent"
  participant BuyerInbox as "Buyer Belong Inbox pool"
  participant BuyerApp as "Buyer's agentic app"
  participant BuyerNotify as "Buyer notification app"
  actor BuyerHuman as "Buyer-side human"

  Note over SellerHuman,BuyerHuman: Phase 1 - Setup and training
  SellerHuman->>SellerApp: $belong-setup-account
  SellerHuman->>SellerApp: $belong-train-selling-agent
  SellerApp->>SellingAgent: Create Service Playbook and Standing Authorization
  SellingAgent->>Marketplace: List Service for semantic discovery
  BuyerHuman->>BuyerApp: $belong-setup-account
  BuyerHuman->>BuyerApp: $belong-train-buying-agent
  BuyerApp->>BuyingAgent: Create Buying Playbook and Standing Authorization
  BuyerHuman->>BuyerApp: $belong-start-buying-request
  BuyerApp->>BuyingAgent: Create Buying Request

  Note over SellerHuman,BuyerHuman: Phase 2 - Search, engagement, discovery, and negotiation
  BuyingAgent->>Marketplace: Search semantically with optional tags
  Marketplace-->>BuyingAgent: Return matching Services and Selling Agents
  BuyingAgent->>SellingAgent: Open direct engagement or competitive RFP feed
  SellingAgent->>BuyingAgent: Send seller-led Discovery Questionnaire
  alt Discovery fits Buying Playbook
    BuyingAgent->>SellingAgent: Answer discovery autonomously
  else Buyer input, authorization, or instruction needed
    BuyingAgent->>BuyerInbox: Add pending buyer Inbox item
    BuyerInbox-->>BuyerNotify: Notify preferred channel: "Check your Belong Inbox"
    BuyerNotify-->>BuyerHuman: Email, Slack, WhatsApp, or similar notification
    BuyerHuman->>BuyerApp: Ask agentic app: "What's in my Belong Inbox?"
    BuyerApp->>BuyerInbox: Fetch and resolve buyer Inbox item
    BuyerApp->>BuyingAgent: Return human response to Buying Agent
  end
  SellingAgent->>BuyingAgent: Send seller-signed Service Contract/SOW Proposal
  Note over SellingAgent,BuyingAgent: Proposal already includes scope, legal terms, billing cycle, payment milestones, acceptance criteria, and platform fee
  BuyingAgent->>BuyingAgent: Compare proposals, negotiate, and check authority
  loop Contract/SOW negotiation if needed
    BuyingAgent->>SellingAgent: Request contract/SOW changes
    SellingAgent->>BuyingAgent: Send revised seller-signed Contract/SOW
  end

  Note over SellerHuman,BuyerHuman: Phase 3 - Legal signing and Active Service creation
  alt Proposal fits Standing Authorization
    BuyingAgent->>SigningProvider: Execute buyer signature inside authority
  else Legal, budget, payment, or authority limit exceeded
    BuyingAgent->>BuyerInbox: Add pending buyer signature authorization item
    BuyerInbox-->>BuyerNotify: Notify preferred channel: "Check your Belong Inbox"
    BuyerNotify-->>BuyerHuman: Email, Slack, WhatsApp, or similar notification
    BuyerHuman->>BuyerApp: Ask agentic app: "What's in my Belong Inbox?"
    BuyerApp->>BuyerInbox: Fetch and resolve signature authorization
    BuyerApp->>SigningProvider: Approve signature or request contract changes
  end
  SigningProvider-->>Marketplace: Return executed Service Contract/SOW and signature audit trail
  Marketplace->>SellingAgent: Create Active Service with seller obligations
  Marketplace->>BuyingAgent: Create Active Service with buyer obligations
  Marketplace->>ReputationAudit: Log executed contract, Playbook versions, and authority checks

  Note over SellerHuman,BuyerHuman: Phase 4 - Contract/SOW billing and Stripe money movement
  Marketplace->>Marketplace: Convert contract/SOW terms into billing events
  Marketplace->>StripeAccounts: Configure buyer payment method, seller connected account, platform fee, and seller net
  alt Signature payment due
    Marketplace->>StripeAccounts: Trigger authorize, charge, hold, collect, or payout per contract/SOW
    StripeAccounts-->>Marketplace: Return ledger event with gross, fee, seller net, hold, release, refund, or collection state
  else Payment exception or out-of-contract movement
    Marketplace->>BuyerInbox: Add buyer payment authorization or exception item
    Marketplace->>SellerInbox: Add seller collections or payout exception item
    BuyerInbox-->>BuyerNotify: Notify preferred channel: "Check your Belong Inbox"
    SellerInbox-->>SellerNotify: Notify preferred channel: "Check your Belong Inbox"
  end

  Note over SellerHuman,BuyerHuman: Phase 5 - Active Service communication, meetings, delivery, and evidence
  SellingAgent->>BuyingAgent: Service messages, information requests, status updates
  BuyingAgent->>SellingAgent: Buyer context, acceptance questions, constraints
  alt Communication needs human or provider-side action
    SellingAgent->>SellerInbox: Add fulfillment, meeting, collections, or exception item
    SellerInbox-->>SellerNotify: Notify preferred channel: "Check your Belong Inbox"
    SellerNotify-->>SellerHuman: Email, Slack, WhatsApp, or similar notification
    SellerHuman->>SellerApp: Ask agentic app: "What's in my Belong Inbox?"
    SellerApp->>SellerInbox: Fetch and resolve seller Inbox item
    BuyingAgent->>BuyerInbox: Add buyer information, authorization, or instruction item
    BuyerInbox-->>BuyerNotify: Notify preferred channel: "Check your Belong Inbox"
    BuyerNotify-->>BuyerHuman: Email, Slack, WhatsApp, or similar notification
    BuyerHuman->>BuyerApp: Ask agentic app: "What's in my Belong Inbox?"
    BuyerApp->>BuyerInbox: Fetch and resolve buyer Inbox item
  end
  alt Human-to-Human Meeting needed
    SellingAgent->>Marketplace: Request meeting for discovery, delivery, escalation, dispute, or relationship context
    BuyingAgent->>Marketplace: Confirm meeting need, agenda, and constraints
    Marketplace->>SellerInbox: Add seller meeting item
    Marketplace->>BuyerInbox: Add buyer meeting item
    SellerInbox-->>SellerNotify: Notify preferred channel: "Check your Belong Inbox"
    BuyerInbox-->>BuyerNotify: Notify preferred channel: "Check your Belong Inbox"
    SellingAgent-->>SellerHuman: Prepare human with brief, agenda, risks, and desired outcome
    BuyingAgent-->>BuyerHuman: Prepare human with brief, agenda, risks, and desired outcome
    SellerHuman->>BuyerHuman: Human-to-Human Meeting by video or in person
    SellerHuman->>SellerApp: Share notes, decisions, and follow-up context
    BuyerHuman->>BuyerApp: Share notes, decisions, and follow-up context
    SellerApp->>SellingAgent: Return meeting notes and instructions
    BuyerApp->>BuyingAgent: Return meeting notes and instructions
    SellingAgent->>Marketplace: Update obligations, follow-ups, evidence, or Change Order need
    BuyingAgent->>Marketplace: Update acceptance context, risks, or dispute posture
  end
  SellingAgent->>Marketplace: Create fulfillment tasks and submit Deliverable Evidence Package
  BuyingAgent->>Marketplace: Review evidence against contract/SOW acceptance criteria
  loop Billing milestone or billing cycle from contract/SOW
    Marketplace->>StripeAccounts: Trigger invoice, authorize, charge, hold, release, refund, collect, payout, platform fee, or seller net event
    StripeAccounts-->>Marketplace: Return payment ledger update
  end
  alt Scope, price, timeline, or deliverables change
    SellingAgent->>BuyingAgent: Negotiate Change Order as signed Contract/SOW amendment
    BuyingAgent->>SigningProvider: Execute amendment if inside authority
    SigningProvider-->>Marketplace: Return executed amendment and audit trail
    Marketplace->>StripeAccounts: Update billing schedule and payment expectations
  end

  Note over SellerHuman,BuyerHuman: Phase 6 - Disputes and Belong Judge
  alt Delivery accepted
    BuyingAgent->>Marketplace: Accept delivery
    Marketplace->>StripeAccounts: Trigger acceptance billing, release, collection, payout, platform fee, and seller net
  else Delivery contested
    BuyingAgent->>SellingAgent: Attempt autonomous dispute resolution inside Buying Playbook and Service Playbook
    SellingAgent->>BuyingAgent: Respond with contract/SOW evidence, messages, payment ledger, meeting notes, and deliverable evidence
    alt Resolved inside Playbooks
      BuyingAgent->>Marketplace: Record revision, refund, acceptance, or Change Order outcome
      Marketplace->>StripeAccounts: Apply agreed hold, refund, release, collection, or payout
    else Outside Playbook, high risk, ambiguous, or party requests review
      Marketplace->>BelongJudge: Send dispute evidence package for autonomous review
      BelongJudge-->>Marketplace: Return autonomous decision and explanation
      alt Human judge escalation needed
        Marketplace->>BuyerInbox: Add buyer Belong Judge escalation item
        Marketplace->>SellerInbox: Add seller Belong Judge escalation item
        BuyerInbox-->>BuyerNotify: Notify preferred channel: "Check your Belong Inbox"
        SellerInbox-->>SellerNotify: Notify preferred channel: "Check your Belong Inbox"
      else Decision can be executed inside Playbooks
        Marketplace->>StripeAccounts: Execute Judge-directed hold, release, refund, collection, or payout
      end
    end
  end

  Note over SellerHuman,BuyerHuman: Phase 7 - Reputation, ratings, audit, and learning
  Marketplace->>ReputationAudit: Update automated reputation from delivery, payment, dispute, evidence, response time, and contract/SOW compliance
  BuyingAgent->>ReputationAudit: Rate Selling Agent from 0 to 5 stars
  SellingAgent->>ReputationAudit: Rate Buying Agent from 0 to 5 stars
  alt Optional manual human rating
    BuyerHuman->>BuyerApp: Add manual service rating
    SellerHuman->>SellerApp: Add manual counterparty rating
    BuyerApp->>ReputationAudit: Record buyer human rating
    SellerApp->>ReputationAudit: Record seller human rating
  end
  ReputationAudit-->>BuyerApp: Reputation, audit events, and Decision Explanations visible through $belong-check-reputation
  ReputationAudit-->>SellerApp: Reputation, audit events, and Decision Explanations visible through $belong-check-reputation
]]></diagram>
  </user_sequence>
  <users>
    <user priority="primary" order="1"><![CDATA[Service Provider human setting up, training, operating, approving, overriding, and supervising one or more Belong Selling Agents, with one Selling Agent dedicated to each Service.]]></user>
    <user priority="primary" order="2"><![CDATA[Buyer-side human setting up, training, operating, approving, overriding, and supervising a Belong Buying Agent to buy and manage Services through the marketplace.]]></user>
  </users>
  <scope>
    <in><![CDATA[First Experience Slice for the Belong Skill Pack: Setup, Training, Validation, and Production flows for Belong Buying Agents and Belong Selling Agents.]]></in>
    <in><![CDATA[Full mocked marketplace lifecycle coverage: Belong Account, Organization Profile, Service, Buying Request, Composite Buying Request, Service Search Result, Engagement Feed, Discovery Questionnaire, Proposal, Service Contract/SOW, Active Service, Marketplace Inbox, Deliverable Evidence Package, Delivery Acceptance, payments/collections events, Change Order, Human-to-Human Meeting, Fulfillment Task, Escalation, Dispute, Belong Judge, Agent Reputation, Audit Log, Decision Explanation, Human Override, Agent Pause, training/retraining recommendations, Provider Optimization, Selling Optimization, Marketplace Privacy Promise, Marketplace Learning Boundary, and Belong Monetization.]]></in>
    <out><![CDATA[Production backend implementation, real Belong agent runtime, real payments, real e-signature execution, real notifications, real semantic search, real reputation scoring, real dispute adjudication, production organization permissions, security/compliance implementation, and external workflow sync.]]></out>
    <out><![CDATA[Bring-your-own-agent support, direct buyer mode, a primary Belong web app, external agent-to-marketplace MCPs, and separate operator/approver user personas.]]></out>
  </scope>
  <human_skill_surface>
    <shared><![CDATA[belong-marketplace-guide, belong-setup-account, belong-inbox, belong-check-active-services, belong-check-payments, belong-check-reputation.]]></shared>
    <buyer><![CDATA[belong-train-buying-agent, belong-start-buying-request, belong-check-buying-requests, belong-steer-buying-agent.]]></buyer>
    <seller><![CDATA[belong-train-selling-agent, belong-check-selling-pipeline, belong-steer-selling-agent.]]></seller>
    <internal><![CDATA[belong-internal-buying-workflow, belong-internal-selling-workflow, belong-internal-active-service-actions, belong-internal-disputes, belong-marketplace-runtime.]]></internal>
  </human_skill_surface>
  <acceptance_signals>
    <signal priority="primary" order="1"><![CDATA[A Service Provider human or buyer-side human can complete OAuth-style authentication, return to the agentic application, and use the Belong Skill Pack for the rest of the experience.]]></signal>
    <signal priority="primary" order="2"><![CDATA[A Service Provider human can create a Service Playbook and activate a Selling Agent for one Service, including monetization, billing, collections, negotiation limits, contract/SOW behavior, delivery workflow, and escalation paths.]]></signal>
    <signal priority="primary" order="3"><![CDATA[A buyer-side human can create a Buying Playbook and activate a Buying Agent, including budget, provider preferences, selection rules, RFP behavior, Standing Authorization, payment rules, acceptance criteria, dispute behavior, and optimization goals.]]></signal>
    <signal priority="primary" order="4"><![CDATA[A mocked Buying Request can move through semantic search, Engagement Feed, seller-led Discovery Questionnaire, seller-signed Service Contract/SOW Proposal, negotiation, buyer signature, Active Service, delivery evidence, Delivery Acceptance, payments/collections events, and Agent Reputation update.]]></signal>
    <signal priority="secondary" order="5"><![CDATA[The Service Provider human and buyer-side human can inspect their Marketplace Inbox and resolve pending information, authorization, instruction/execution, fulfillment, meeting, dispute, payment exception, Change Order approval, pause/resume, and operational intervention requests.]]></signal>
    <signal priority="secondary" order="6"><![CDATA[The buyer-side human can experience Provider Optimization and a Composite Buying Request, while the Service Provider human can experience Selling Optimization, without either side leaving the conversational Skill Pack surface.]]></signal>
    <signal priority="secondary" order="7"><![CDATA[Every user story in the Linear PRD can be exercised through mocked Guided Work, producing stateful marketplace outputs and human-readable summaries.]]></signal>
  </acceptance_signals>
  <risks_and_open_questions>
    <item><![CDATA[The First Experience Slice covers many marketplace behaviors; the main risk is making the guided experience too broad or tiring while still proving the whole lifecycle.]]></item>
    <item><![CDATA[The exact Signing Provider and exact Stripe agentic-commerce product fit remain open and should be resolved in later provider or architecture work.]]></item>
    <item><![CDATA[The Skill Pack must make autonomy and escalation feel safe for the two human users: each needs to understand what their agent can do alone, what it cannot do alone, and how to override or pause it.]]></item>
  </risks_and_open_questions>
</prd>
